Guide to the Kathy Hopwood Papers, 1970-2015 and undated RL.11387
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kathy Hopwood papers
1970-2015 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kathy, Hopwood
Seigler, Beth
RL.11387
46.5 Linear Feet 31 boxes numbered 1-33; numbering skips boxes 9-10
Kathy Hopwood is a martial arts and self-defense teacher who founded the SafeSkills Dojo in Durham, NC. She and her partner Beth Seigler provided both martial arts classes and women's self-defense programs. The collection contains materials documenting workshops and training courses they oversaw and participated in, as well as materials from women's organizations that were dedicated to the goal of promoting women's self-defense capabilities and expertise in the martial arts. It contains professional materials as well as educational materials, publications and articles about self-defense and martial arts, especially pertaining to women and children.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of listening or viewing copies.
Provenance
The Kathy Hopwood papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015-2017.
Biographical / Historical
Kathy Hopwood, working with her partner Beth Seigler, created martial arts and self-defense workshops and training courses for women in order to equip them to defend themselves against assault, rape, and other forms of attack. She also dedicated considerable work to the promotion of child safety, self-defense for older adults, and self-defense for individuals with disabilities. She oversaw the opening of her own dojo in Durham, North Carolina, which was active from 1982-2015. The organization's name changed over time: it was founded in 1982 as the Triangle Women's Karate Association. When Beth Seigler partnered with Hopwood, its name changed to Triangle Women's Martial Arts, located at 715 Mangum Street in Durham, and then finally to SafeSkills Dojo in 1992 when they relocated to 3710 Shannon Road. In 2008, they related to their final space at 3702 Hillsborough Road in Durham.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of materials documenting Kathy Hopwood's work in the areas of women's martial arts and self-defense in the Triangle area of North Carolina. Materials from her SafeSkills Dojo comprise self-defense training manuals, course and workshop materials, newsletters, organizational history, some correspondence, and the individual work of both Hopwood and her partner Beth Seigler. Press clippings document mentions of Hopwood, Seigler, and their dojo in print media, largely from Triangle-area publications. Materials from the National Women's Martial Arts Federation (NWMAF) provide documentation of that organization's history, particularly its early years. Hopwood and Seigler were both very active in the organization, and Hopwood served as its archivist for a 10-year period. There is also extensive documentation of NWMAF's yearly training camps for women and girls. Materials from other women's martial arts groups across the country are well-documented, as are materials on sexual assault and rape prevention, particularly from the Triangle area. Also included are books and periodicals on the topic of women's martial arts and self-defense. Photographs document the dojo's work, as well as national training sessions conducted by Hopwood and Seigler. Other audio-visual material consists of training films and examples of the dojo's instructors at work.
banner
This collection is currently being reprocessed to improve description and is unavailable until approximately March 2023. For more information, please contact the Rubenstein Library.
Martial arts -- North Carolina; Martial arts for children; Self-defense for children; Self-defense for women; Self-defense for women -- Periodicals; Sex crimes -- Prevention; Women in martial arts; Women in martial arts -- Periodicals; Audiocassettes; Videocassettes; Audiovisual materials; SafeSkills (Durham, N.C.); National Women's Martial Arts Federation; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- SafeSkills Dojo, 1972-2015 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of materials generated by and relating to the North Carolina dojo founded by Kathy Hopwood, known over time as the Triangle Women's Karate Association, Triangle Women's Martial Arts, and finally SafeSkills. Largely consists of programming and educational materials focusing on self-defense strategies for women and children. Includes some correspondence and files documenting the individual work of Hopwood and Siegler. Also includes organizational newsletters published by the dojo over the years, published articles by Kathy Hopwood, and a booklet entitled Touching the Past detailing the organization's history in Box 23.
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Box 3)
  - Kata (Box 2)
  - Fighting Information Manuals (Box 2)
  - Martial Arts Uniforms Cut Outs (Box 3)
  - First TWKA T-Shirt and Other Apparel (Box 3)
  - TWMA Center- SafeSkills: Sexual and Gender Harassment Resources Binder, 1994-1999; 3 folders (Box 16)
  - TWMA Center Self-Defense Information, 1983-1994 (Box 16)
  - Rape and Violence Against Women Resources, 1979-1994 (Box 16)
  - Children's Self-Defense Binder, 1983-1991 (Box 16)
  - TWMA Center - Personal Safety Skills Training: Self-Defense Books #1-2 and 5-10 (Box 16)
  - Triangle Women's Martial Arts - Rank and Tests (Box 22)
  - Arnis (Box 22)
  - Walking the Body: A Black Belt Project by Megan Noor (Box 22)
  - Demonstrations, 1993 (Box 22)
  - Triangle Women's Martial Arts - General Martial Arts Materials (Box 22)
  - Triangle Women's Martial Arts - Sparring Materials (Box 22)
  - Triangle Women's Martial Arts - Weapons Materials (Box 22)
  - Hopwood Resume, 1976 (Box 23)
  - Black Belt Certification - Kathy Hopwood and Marianna Kaufman, 1982 (Box 23)
  - Early Teaching, 1982 (Box 23)
  - Martial Arts Training Notes: Hopwood and Seigler (Box 23)
  - Arnis-Filipino Martial Arts Teaching Notes - Hopwood and Seigler, 1985 (Box 23)
  - Teaching Notes - Seigler (Box 23)
  - Booklet: Touching the Past - History of SafeSkills Dojo, 2015 (Box 23)
  - Triangle Women's Karate Association Materials, 1984-1989 (Box 23)
  - Martial Arts in NC, 1973 (Box 23)
  - Triangle Women's Karate Association (TWKA), 1983 (Box 23)
  - TWKA Calendars, Classes, Workshops, Demos, 1983 (Box 23)
  - TWKA Karate Posters and Layout Boards (Box 23)
  - TWKA Self-Defense Posters and Layout Boards (Box 23)
  - Triangle Women's Martial Arts (TWMA) Mangum St. Posters and Layout Boards (Box 23)
  - TWMA - Shannon Plaza Posters and Layout Boards (Box 23)
  - TWMA Logo Originals (Box 23)
  - TWMA Calendars, Classes, Workshops, Demos, 1986 (Box 23)
  - TWKA/TWMA Student Handbook, 1983 (Box 23)
  - Early Years Teaching Children's Karate (Box 23)
  - TWMA Transition Phase, 1986 (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills Associates Transition to SafeSkills Inc., 1990s (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills: SafeKids classes at Shannon Plaza, 1992 (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills Girl's Karate Classes - Ages 6-14 (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills Girl's Karate Book, 1994 (Box 23)
  - TWMA Girl's Karate Book - 2nd and 3rd Dojo Booklets (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills Summer Camps for Children (Box 23)
  - Children's Karate Class Teaching Notes (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills KinderKarate Classes - Hillsborough Road dojo (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills Manual for Parents- Children's Karate Classes (Box 23)
  - TWMA and SafeSkills' Belt Certificate Forms Notes (Box 23)
  - Beth Seigler - Belt Test Materials, 1987 (Box 23)
  - SafeSkills Student Blue Belt Written Exam (Box 23)
  - Dave Lowry (Box 23)
  - Task Reports by Karate Students (Box 23)
  - Black Belt Projects (Box 23)
  - Special Training Camp Application Materials, 2005 (Box 23)
  - Community Demonstrations/Participation, 1980 (Box 24)
  - Public Demonstrations Notes, 1980s (Box 24)
  - Kiai: A Film, 1984 (Box 24)
  - UNC Self-Defense Presentations, 1985 (Box 24)
  - UNC-Chapel Hill SafeSkills Training and Development Classes, 1996-2006 (Box 24)
  - Duke Self-Defense Lectures, Workshops, 1980 (Box 24)
  - TWMA Student Materials (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Associates, 1992 (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Corporate Programs, 1990-1992 (Box 24)
  - Business Travel Safety Teaching Notes/Handouts (Box 24)
  - Armed Assailants Defense Teaching Notes/Handouts (Box 24)
  - Multiple Attacker Teaching Notes/Handouts (Box 24)
  - Older Adults Self-Defense Materials (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Handouts (Box 24)
  - Children's Self-Defense Teaching Notes (Box 24)
  - Self-Defense for Teen Girls, 1990 (Box 24)
  - TWMA/SafeSkills Self-Defense for LGBT (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills' EmPOWERment Course Teaching Notes (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills' EmPOWERment Course Poster/Promo Materials, 1992-1997 (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Defuse/De-Escalation Programs (Box 24)
  - Options TWMA program for Duke Orientation, 1989 (Box 24)
  - Success! Self-Defense Accounts (Box 24)
  - Self-Defense Success Stories (Box 24)
  - Various TWKA/TWMA-SafeSkills Business Cards (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills, Inc. Logo, 1990 (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Posters (Box 24)
  - TWKA, TWMA-Dojo and SafeSkills Brochures (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Calendars, Classes, Workshops, Demos, 1993 (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Dojo Relocation, 2008 (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Corporate Promotional Booklet (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills Marketing Materials (Box 24)
  - PSAs and Ads for TWKA/TWMA and SafeSkills (Box 24)
  - Print Media PSA Booklet (Box 24)
  - National Directory of Self-Defense Instructors by SafeSkills Associates, 1991 (Box 24)
  - SafeSkills, Inc. Trademark Papers (Box 27)
  - EmPOWERment SafeSkills Mock Attacker Program Materials, 1993 (Box 28)
  - Thank You Letters (Box 24)
  - Self Defense for Adult Women Teaching Notes - Hopwood and Seigler (Box 24)
  - One Hour Tacks: SafeSkills Notes/Handouts - Hopwood-Seigler (Box 24)
  - Certificates and Awards - Hopwood and Seigler (Box 24)
  - Kathy Hopwood's Original Artwork (Box 26, Box 28, Box 32)
  - TWKA Newsletters, 1983-1987 (Box 26)
  - TWMA Dojo Newsletters (Box 26)
  - SafeSkills Newsletters, 1990 (Box 26)
  - Articles by Kathy Hopwood (Box 26)
  - Kathy Hopwood's Writings, 18 folders (Box 32)
    Drafts, notes, thoughts, reflections and papers about self-defense and martial arts, focusing on the why and how of teaching and what social obstacles are in the way.
  - Black, Blue, and Brown Belts Earned by Kathy Hopwood and Beth Seigler (Box 33)
- Press Clippings, 1980-2008 and undated
  Media coverage of Kathy Hopwood's work, articles in which Hopwood is quoted, and articles and newsletters written by Hopwood.
  - UNC Daily Tar Heel
    - Women's Karate Group Teaches Practical Defense, 1985 (Box 25)
    - Courses Teach Women to React in Self Defense, 1983 (Box 26)
    - Seminar to Teach Self Defense, 1984 (Box 26)
    - Rape Programs Provide Defense Tips, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Letter to the Editor, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Art of Self Defense Valuable Skill for Women to Avert Sexual Assault, Rape, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Students Learn Self-Defense Skills, 2008 (Box 26)
  - Durham Morning Herald and Herald Sun
    - Women as Fighters and Winners, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Rule #1 in K-Class- Kids Can't Show Off- Ever, 1987 (Box 26)
    - Police: No Gang Rapes, 1993 (Box 26)
    - Letter to the Editor, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Women's Karate School Uses New Teaching Style, 1986 (Box 26)
    - Photo Spread, 1988 (Box 26)
    - Amanda Smith articles, 1989-1990 (Box 26)
    - Articles on Mace, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Attacks Spark Flood of Calls to Police, 1992 (Box 26)
    - Attacks Put Spotlight on Triangle Self-Defense, 1992 (Box 26)
    - Holiday Crime Prevention, 1994 (Box 26)
    - Women's Karate School Uses New Technique, Style, 1986 (Box 28)
    - Editorial reaction to letter to editor, 1991 (Box 28)
    - Durham on the Defense, 1991 (Box 28)
    - Class Teaches Women the Art of Self-Defense, 1991 (Box 28)
    - SafeSkills Helps Women Develop Plan of Attack, 1992 (Box 28)
    - Women on Defense, 1993 (Box 28)
    - Self-Defense Protects Women, 1994 (Box 28)
  - The Raleigh News & Observer
    - Karate Tests Control Teaches Confidence, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Teens Learn Self-Defense, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Program Helps Kids Learn to Play it Safe, 1992 (Box 26)
    - Self-Protection Course Aimed at Women, 1993 (Box 26)
    - Crime Count No Gauge of Triangle Unease, 1995 (Box 26)
  - Chapel Hill Herald
    - Letter to the Editor, 1992 (Box 26)
    - Women's Self-Defense Way of Life, Not Bag of Tricks, 1990 (Box 26)
    - More Women Seek Self-Defense Skills, 1990 (Box 26)
    - Woman Jogger Murdered, 1993 (Box 26)
    - Women Urged to Just Shout No, 1993 (Box 26)
    - Kathy Hopwood and Beth Siegler guest columns, 1990-1992 (Box 28)
  - Other Publications
    - Self Defense Calls for Fighting Dirty, 1980 (Box 26)
    - Aeolus Duke University: Women Talk About the Unspeakable, 1982 (Box 26)
    - TWKA-SafeSkills RCC Workshops in NC, 1984-2004 (Box 26)
    - Attention All Women! You Can Stop Being Victims (Box 26)
    - Take Back the Night March, Chapel Hill, 1984 (Box 26)
    - Resisting Rape - Self Defense not Depo-Provera, 1984 (Box 26)
    - The Carolina Times: Dummy Takes A Kicking as Women Learn Karate, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Southern Feminist: Non-Competitive Karate Taught at All-Woman School, 1987 (Box 26)
    - The Newsletter: Interview, 1988 (Box 26)
    - Inner Views: TWMA Center, 1988 (Box 26)
    - Center Notes: Your body - Your Safety, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Duke Chronicle: Self-Defense for Women Workshops, 1989-2002 (Box 26)
    - NCSU Alumni Magazine: Don't Be in the Dark, 1990 (Box 26)
    - The News of Orange County: Training Helps Women Defend Against Attackers, 1992 (Box 26)
    - Rape Cards, 1992 (Box 26, Box 28)
    - Fifty-Plus articles, 1992-2011 (Box 26)
    - Triangle Woman articles, 1992-2003 (Box 26)
    - Carolina Parent: Putting Safety Before Manners, 1993 (Box 26)
    - Women's Self Defense Magazine: How to Choose a Self-Defense Course, 1984 (Box 26)
    - Business Leader Magazine, 1994-2011 (Box 26)
    - NCSU Technician, 1992-1994 (Box 26)
    - Tae Kwon Do: Why Do Women Train?, 1997 (Box 26)
    - The Independent: First Person- Mastering the Follow-Through, 1998 (Box 26)
    - Carolina Alumni Review: SafeSkills Seminar Teaches How to Fight Off Attack, 1999 (Box 26)
    - Outer Banks Sentinel: Self-Defense is Attitude, Technique (Box 26)
    - Kathy as Artist, 2000 (Box 26)
    - Tamara Ohr Ross Cartoons (Box 26)
    - Victimology: An International Journal; Volume 7, Numbers 1-4, 1982 (Box 26)
    - Triangle Business: A Defensive Duo, 1990 (Box 28)
    - Off Our Backs: Women and Self-Defense Weapons by Kathy Hopwood, 1991 (Box 28)
    - Duke Dialogue: TWMA Options Program, 1989 (Box 26)
    - Duke Dialogue: Women's Center sponsored TWMA Workshop, 1990 (Box 26)
    - Raleigh Extra: In World of Assaults, Class Teaches Skills for Survival, 1992 (Box 26)
    - Raleigh Extra: Police: Rapes not Connected and Group Fights Public Perception of Rape, 1992 (Box 26)
    - Raleigh Extra: Attacks Put Spotlight on Triangle Self-Defense, 1992 (Box 28)
- National Women's Martial Arts Federation, 1976-2014 and undated
  Materials related to this national organization in which Hopwood and Siegler were active. Chiefly consists of materials from yearly training camps. Kathy Hopwood was the organization's first archivist, and kept the most complete set of materials from 1988-1995. Includes original NWMAF logo designed by Kathy Hopwood.
  - Steering Committee Notes (Box 4)
  - Brochures (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Bylaws (Box 4)
  - Archives - Herstory of NWMAF (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1982-2014 (Box 5)
  - Special Training Camps, 1992-2006 (Box 12)
  - Publicity/Outreach Committee (Box 12)
  - Regional Training, 1992 (Box 12)
  - Special Training Materials, 2007-2010 (Box 12)
  - NWMAF and The Pacific Association of Women Martial Artists Combined Camp Materials, 1994-1995 (Box 12)
  - Special Training Camp, Chicago, IL, 1991 (Box 12)
  - Special Training Camp, New Haven, CT, 1990 (Box 12)
  - Special Training Camp, San Luis Obispo, CA, 1989 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Geneva, NY, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Kent State University, Kent, OH, 1987 (Box 13)
  - Teacher's Conference in Geneva, NY, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Yale, New Haven, CT, 1986 (Box 13)
  - National Self Defense Teaching Practicum Columbus, OH, 1983 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Geneva, NY, 1985 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Edinboro, PA, 1984 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Lawrenceville, NJ, 1983 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Provincetown, MA, 1982 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, East Lansing, MI, 1981 (Box 13)
  - Valley Women's Martial Arts (Box 13)
  - The Karate School for Women "Teacher's Conference" - NYC (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Suffield, CT, 1980 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Rochester/Detroit, MI, 1979 (Box 13)
  - Regional Event Camp, Buffalo, NY, 1978 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camp, Northampton, MA, 1977 (Box 13)
  - Special Training: Nancy Lehmann - Meechee Dojo Materials, 1976 (Box 13)
  - DC Teacher's Conference: Ja Shin Do sponsor, 1976 (Box 13)
  - Minneapolis, MN, 1976 (Box 13)
  - Special Training Camps - Handouts for Instructors (Box 24)
  - National Women's Martial Arts Federation Logo Drawing Designed by Kathy Hopwood, 1988 (Box 24)
  - National Women's Martial Arts Federation Logo Patches Designed by Kathy Hopwood (Box 33)
- Women's Martial Arts and Self-Defense Resources, 1970-2000s and undated
  This series contains materials documenting martial arts and self-defense programs for women and children elsewhere in the country. Largely consists of materials from regional organizations, and provides an overview of other programs similar to the ones run by Hopwood in North Carolina.
  - Women in the Martial Arts, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Kid Power Project (Box 6)
  - Child Assault Prevention (Box 6)
  - Strategies for Free Children (Box 6)
  - Family Protection (Box 6)
  - Safe Child Program (Box 16)
  - Children: Self-Protection Issues/Information (Box 16)
  - Children's Safety Resources (Box 27)
  - Chimera (Box 11)
  - Canadian Groups (Box 11)
  - F.I.S.T. Ohio - Sunny Graff (Box 11)
  - Association of Women's Martial Arts Instructors (Box 11)
  - South Carolina Women's Consortium (Box 11)
  - Women Safe (Box 11)
  - SAFE NYC (Box 11)
  - New York Women's Martial Arts and Self-Defense (Box 11)
  - Mary Brandl (Box 11)
  - Survival for Women Newsletters, 1981-1983 (Box 11)
  - Alternatives (Box 11)
  - F.I.S.T. - Olympia, Washington (Box 11)
  - Los Angeles Commission on Assaults Against Women - Patti Giggans (Box 11)
  - National Coalition Against Sexual Assault (Box 11)
  - Impact - Model Mugging (Box 11)
  - American Women's Self Defense Association, 1990 (Box 11)
  - We are AWARE Newsletters, 1990-1993 (Box 11)
  - Women's Martial Arts Union, NY, 1972-1976 (Box 14)
  - Feminist Karate Union - Py Bateman - Seattle (Box 14)
  - Feminist Karate Union - Bobbi Snyder - Pittsburgh, PA (Box 14)
  - Pacific Association of Women Martial Artists (Box 14)
  - Thousand Waves - Chicago, IL (Box 14)
  - Midwest Women's Martial Arts Training Weekend, Bloomington, Indiana, 1984 (Box 14)
  - Tai Chi Ch'uan Association of Indiana - Laura Stone (Box 14)
  - International (Box 14)
  - WMAU NYC Meeting Notes (Box 14)
  - Photos - ID File (Box 14)
  - Banshee Nutcracker's Suite (Box 14)
  - AWMAI (Box 14)
  - Women's Self Defense Alliance (Box 14)
  - Hand to Hand: Kajukenbo Self Defense Center - Coleen Gragen - Oakland (Box 14)
  - Karate Women California (Box 14)
  - Carol Middleton - D.C. Self Defense Karate Association (Box 14)
  - Virginia (Box 14)
  - The Valley Women's Martial Arts School (Box 14)
  - Flying Tiger Martial Arts (Box 14)
  - Joan Nelson - Movement Arts, Michigan- Dojo (Box 14)
  - Jaye Spiro - Mejishi/Detroit Dojo (Box 14)
  - Feminist Eclectic Martial Arts - Kore Grate (Box 14)
  - Roberta Schine - NYC, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Women Warriors - NY Sue Ribner (Box 14)
  - NYU Li Tao - Marcia Klein Kenpo-San (Box 14)
  - Brooklyn Women's Martial Arts (Box 14)
  - Okinawan Karate - Pam Wren; Kent, Ohio (Box 14)
  - Chicago Women's Seido (Box 14)
  - Karate for Women - Marianna Kaufman - Atlanta, GA, 1970s (Box 14)
  - First Southern Women's Martial Arts Weekend, 1982 (Box 14)
  - Seven Star Women's Kung-Fu Kajukenbo (Box 14)
- Rape and Sexual Assault Resources, 1980-2000 and undated
  Contains materials related to the issue of rape and sexual assault, with a focus on martial arts and self-defense strategies. Materials have a local focus on the Triangle area of North Carolina, especially the Orange County Rape Crisis Center.
  - Karate and Sexual Assault (Box 4)
  - Acquaintance Rape and Sexual Assault Prevention Training Manual (Box 4)
  - Research (Box 4)
  - Feminist Articles (Box 4)
  - Materials and Resources for Young Victims of Sexual Abuse (Box 7)
  - Rape and Sexual Assault Prevention (Box 7)
  - F.I.S.T.: Feminists in Self Defense Training (Box 7)
  - Rape Prevention Leader's Guide (Box 7)
  - WAR Ohio - Rape Prevention Workshops: A Group Leader's Guide (Box 7)
  - Orange County Rape Crisis Center Manual, 1983 (Box 7)
  - Rape: Facts About Awareness and Prevention (Box 7)
  - Sexual Assault Intervention Handbook by the University of Michigan Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (Box 7)
  - Date Rape and Rape Prevention Materials (Box 7)
  - Duke Dare Training Manual (Box 7)
  - Battered Women Resources (Box 11)
  - Myths and Facts About Rape and Sexual Assault (Box 11)
  - Gay and Lesbian Self Defense Issues (Box 11)
  - Older Adults Resources (Box 11)
  - Disabled Self-Defense (Box 11)
  - Men - Rape Issues (Box 11)
  - Gang Rapes (Box 11)
  - Racism and Rape (Box 11)
  - Harassment of Women (Box 11)
  - Survivors (Box 11)
  - Rape and Violence Against Women Resources (Box 16)
  - Orange County Women's Center - Self-Defense/Karate, 1980 (Box 24)
  - Orange County Rape Crisis Center Newsletters (Box 24)
  - Durham Rape Crisis Center (Box 24)
  - YMCA Durham, 1980-1986 (Box 24)
  - Raleigh Women's Center (Box 24)
  - NC Coalition Against Sexual Assault - Conferences/SafeSkills Workshops, 1998-2000 (Box 24)
  - NC State University - Women's Center Self-Defense Workshops, 1980s (Box 24)
  - Rape/Sexual Assault on Campus (Box 24)
  - Research - Self-Defense, Fear, Rapists (Box 24)
  - Local Martial Artist, School Owner, Convicted Rapist- Triangle Area, 1992 (Box 24)
- Publications, 1972-2004 and undated
  Periodicals books, reference materials, and other published works related to self-defense with a focus on women's issues.
  - Promotional Materials and Letters, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Black Belt Woman Issues, Volume 1, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Ja Shin Do and Dana Densmore, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Ja Shin Do - DC School Conflicts, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Continental Directory of Martial Arts and Self Defense Schools and Classes for Women, 1976 (Box 1)
  - No More Fun and Games Issue 3: The Dialectics of Sexism, 1972 (Box 1)
  - No More Fun and Games Issue 5: The First Revolution, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Fighting Woman News Calendar, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Women in the Martial Arts Calendars, 1984-1990 (Box 1)
  - Aegis Magazine on Ending Violence Against Women, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - Directory for Martial Artists with Disabilities, 1989 (Box 1)
  - The National Directory of Self Protection Instructors, 1991 (Box 1)
  - National Women's Martial Arts Federation Member Directory, 2000-2004 (Box 1)
  - Fighting Woman News, 1975-1996 (Box 2)
  - Mainstream Women's Magazine Clippings (Box 4)
  - Men's Martial Arts in Mainstream Publications Clippings (Box 4, Box 24)
  - Self Protection Materials (Box 6)
  - Terrorism in America Discussion Guide (Box 6)
  - Oriental Martial Arts Instruction Manual (Box 6)